Finding Aid for American Association of University Professors University of Michigan Chapter
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Association of University Professors, University of Michigan Chapter, records 1926-1995
American Association of University Professors. University of Michigan Chapter.
3 linear ft.
85598 Bh 2
The records of the American Association of University Professors, University of Michigan Chapter include adminsitrative files, agendas, meeting minutes, correspondence, membership lists, and newsltters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received in a series of accessions from the secretaries of the AAUP-UM Chapter (Donor # 3928 ).
The records are open to research.
The American Association of University Professors (AAUP) was founded in 1915 to defend faculty rights, especially academic freedom and tenure. The AAUP protects professors from arbitrary dismissal and harassment and assures due process when a professor is charged with incompetence or moral turpitude, the two most common grounds for dismissal. The University of Michigan Chapter of the AAUP, evidently formed in the mid-1920s, defends the rights of the faculty of the University of Michigan. As one might expect given the collegiality of university professors, the local chapter maintains a close relationship with the national AAUP.
Within the chapter, these bonds of collegiality are often strained as freethinking individuals bridle at acting in concert. This is manifest, for example, in the Nickerson and Davis dismissal case of the mid-1950s during the McCarthy era. This appeared to be a clear cut case of preventing the arbitrary dismissal of colleagues for their leftist politics. Despite extensive efforts, the chapter was unable to prevent the dismissal of Nickerson and Davis; some attribute this failure to a group of the faculty which esteemed conformity over academic freedom. The University of Michigan Chapter of the AAUP survived this episode and continues its work to protect the freedom and rights of the professoriate.
The records of the American Association of University Professors - University of Michigan Chapter consist of three linear feet of agendas and minutes, correspondence and memoranda, reports, financial records, newsletters, and membership lists. These material are arranged in three series: Minutes (1926-1995); Papers, (1932-1995), and Topical Files (1934-1995). The first two series are arranged chronologically; the third series is arranged alphabetically by topic. As these records came to the library in a series of accessions, there is some inconsistency, overlap, and interpenetration between the series. The researcher should consult all three series.
Of special note are the Nickerson and Davis case files in the Topical Files which document the chapter's efforts to prevent the dismissal of these men during the McCarthy era.
Subjects:
American Association of University Professors. University of Michigan Chapter.; Davis, Chandler.; Nickerson, Mark.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Minutes
  - 1926-1995, 12 folders (Box 1)
- Papers
  - 1932-1947, 20 folders (Box 1)
  - 1948-1961, 14 folders (Box 2)
  - 1971-1979, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1980-1995, 11 folders (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  - Constitution, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Davis Case, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Harassment Case, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Kraus Case, 1934-1939 (Box 3)
  - Membership Lists, 1935-1956, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletters, 1982-1995 (Box 3)
  - Nickerson and Davis Cases, 1954-1958, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Retrenchment/Reallocation, 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - Tenure, 1981-1988